Guide to the Sylvia Hall Thompson Papers TAM.639
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Sylvia Hall Thompson Papers
1940-1985
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Thompson, Sylvia, 1924-2012
TAM.639
3 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons
This collection contains the papers of union organizer and Communist Party member Sylvia Hall Thompson (1924-2012). Thompson's papers primarily consists of Freedom of Information Act release files related to Federal Bureau of Investigation surveillance of Hall throughout the 1950s and 1960s. The collection also contains a small portion of material related to Sylvia's first huband Samuel Hall as well as material related to her second husband Robert George Thompson and the Thompson v. McNamara case.
Historical/Biographical Note
Sylvia Hall Thompson (1924-2012) was born Sylvia Bernard in San Antonio, Texas. As a young woman, she joined the Communist Party and helped launch the Civil Rights Congress in Texas. In 1947, she traveled to North Carolina where she spent more than a year organizing electrical workers to join the union. It was there that she met her first husband, Sam Hall, a district organizer for the Party. The young couple moved to Birmingham, Alabama where, as open communists, they endured constant surveillance, threats and break-ins.
After Hall’s death, Sylvia moved to New York City where she went to work for the State Party office and met her second husband, Robert G. Thompson in late 1957. Bob Thompson had been a battalion commander with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in Spain, and went on to receive one of the highest medals for valor – the Distinguished Service Cross – for his heroic actions in the Pacific Theater in World War II.
When he died in 1965, Sylvia sought and received permission from the Army to have his ashes interred in Arlington National Cemetery. However, when publicity about Bob’s previous imprisonment as a Smith Act defendant surfaced, the Army reversed itself and denied the widow’s request. Sylvia contested the Army's decision and in 1968, a federal appeals court ordered the Army to inter Bob Thompson’s ashes.
In subsequent years, Sylvia became a mainstay in the New York office of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, working with veterans and organizing the annual reunions. Sylvia Thompson passed away in 2012.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains the papers of union organizer and Communist Party member Sylvia Hall Thompson. The majority of this collection relates to Sylvia's efforts to have her second husband Robert George Thompson interred in Arlington National Cemetery. A large portion of the collection also consists of Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) FBI Files on Sylvia Hall Thompson. See Series level scope and contents notes for further descriptions.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Sylvia Thompson bequeathed two boxes of her personal papers to Tamiment Library in 2013. The accession number associated with this gift is 2013.047. The Robert George Thompson Papers (previously TAM 075), which were also donated by Sylvia Thompson, were incorporated into this collection in 2014. The accession number associated with this material is 1950.142.
Appraisal
No materials were separated from this collection.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into thrree series as follows:
Series I: Samuel Hall and Robert George Thompson Materials
Series II: Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) FBI Files on Sylvia Thompson
Series III: Thompson v. McNamara Trial Materials
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Researchers interested in using audiovisual materials in this collection (films, cassette tapes, VHS tapes, et cetera) must use a digitized copy, which we refer to as an access copy. Researchers may view an item’s original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection’s finding aid and can be requested in our reading room; materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. These requests are free of charge and can be made in anticipation of your visit. The process typically takes four to six weeks. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A librarian will respond to you with further information.
World War, 1939-1945 |x Veterans.; Abraham Lincoln Brigade.; Communist trials -- United States.; Communists -- United States.; Federal Bureau of Investigation surveillance files.; Arlington National Cemetery (Arlington, Va.); Thompson, Robert George, 1915-1966.; Hall, Samuel Joseph, 1910-1954
- Series I: Samuel Hall and Robert George Thompson Materials
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I contains a small portion of material related to Sylvia's first husband Samuel Hall such as a marriage certificate, photographs, Sylvia Hall Thompson's reminisces of her husband, and clippings related to Hall's activism and his death in 1954. Material related to Robert Thompson includes a marriage certificate, correspondence, and photographs.This series also contains several articles by Robert Thompson, which were published in Political Affairs and materials related to Sylvia Hall Thompson's involvement with the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade.
  - "New Apartment" [material relating to Samuel Hall including marriage certificate, death certificate and photographs], 1945-1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, correspondence and writings pertaining to Robert Thompson and Arlington burial (includes Communist Party publications), 1968-1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Materials relating to Robert Thompson's invovlement in the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (includes photographs and mandatory release form), 1943-1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Facsimiles of original material pertaining to Robert Thompson's life and death [possibly trial exhibits], 1943-1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - FBI correspondence and excerpt of material Sylvia Thompson requested under FOIA, Apr 28, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Political Affairs, 1949-1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Marriage certificate (Sylvia and Robert Thompson) and death certificate of Robert Thompson, 1962, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photographs of Robert Thompson, Sylvia Thompson and others (includes Spanish Civil War songbook), 1943-1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Brief of Appellant Thompson v. McNamara and Robert Thompson letter to Chairman of Soviet War Veteran's Committee, 1965, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters from Robert Thompson to Sylvia Thompson, 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series II: Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) FBI FIles on Sylvia Thompson
  Series II primarily consists of Freedom of Information Act release files related to Federal Bureau of Investigation surveillance of Hall throughout the 1950s and 1960s. Thompson requested copies of these files in the 1980s. Correspondence between Thompson and various government agencies is also included. Additionally, this series contains one cassette tape titled "Nuchow interview" and an encased coin commemorating the 50th anniversary of the Antifascist Spanish War.
  - FBI Files #100-10183, #100-100351 (volumes 25, 26, 2) requested by Sylvia Thompson, 1952-1953, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - FBI Files #100-9335, #100-100351 (volumes 28, 22) requested by Sylvia Thompson, 1951-1967 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - FBI File #100-100351 (includes correspondence between Sylvia Thompson and FBI), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - FBI File #100-100351 (volume 23) requested by Sylvia Thompson, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence from Air Force, IRS, FBI and CIA concerning file requests made by Sylvia Thompson, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - FBI File #100-100351 (volume 27) requested by Sylvia Thompson, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - FBI FIle #100-7320 (volume 2) requested by Sylvia Thompson, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - FBI File #100-100351 (volume 12) requested by Sylvia Thompson, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - FBI File #100-100351 (volume 8) requested by Sylvia Thompson, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Various FBI files pertaining to Sylvia Thompson (includes #100-14687, #100-8808 and others), 1952 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence from FBI to Jeffrey L. Kreisberg regarding Sylvia Thompson file requests, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - FBI File #100-100351 (volume 17) requested by Sylvia Thompson, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Various FBI files pertaining to Sylvia Thompson, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - FBI File #100-100351 (volume 9) requested by Sylvia Thompson, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Various FBI files pertaining to Sylvia Thompson (includes #100-100351, #100-347609 and others), 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Various FBI files pertaining to Sylvia Thompson (includes #100-100351), 1954 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - FBI File #100-100351 (volume 15) requested by Sylvia Thompson, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - FBI File #100-100351 (volume 21) requested by Sylvia Thompson, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - FBI File #100-100351 (volume 1A Supplement) requested by Sylvia Thompson, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Various FBI files pertaining to Sylvia Thompson, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - FBI File #100-100351 (volume 16) requested by Sylvia Thompson, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Various FBI files pertaining to Sylvia Thompson, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - FBI File #100-100351 (volume sub files A and B) requested by Sylvia Thompson, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - FBI File #100-37819 (volume 2) requested by Sylvia Thompson, 1954-1956 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - FBI File #100-100351 (volume 5) requested by Sylvia Thompson, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - FBI File #100-100351 (volume 3) requested by Sylvia Thompson, 1950-1953 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - FBI File #100-100351 (volume 7) requested by Sylvia Thompson, circa 1945 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Various FBI files pertaining to Sylvia Thompson (includes #100-7643, #100-7320, #100-3825 and others), 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Various FBI files pertaining to Sylvia Thompson (includes #100-100351, #100-7320 and others), 1955 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - FBI Files #100-100351 (volumes 16, 18,19), #100-43857 requested by Sylvia Thompson and Kreisberg correspondence, 1959-1960, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - FBI FIle #100-100351 (volume 1) requested by Sylvia Thompson, 1951-1954 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - FBI File #100-100351 (volume 30) requested by Sylvia Thompson, 1967-1971 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Various FBI files pertaining to Sylvia Thompson (includes #100-100351), 1963-1966 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Various FBI files pertaining to Sylvia Thompson (includes #100-100351), 1966-1970 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Various FBI files pertaining to Sylvia Thompson (includes #100-100351), 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - FBI FIle #100-100351 (volume 13) requested by Sylvia Thompson, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence between Sylvia Thompson and FBI, CIA and others (includes photographs and notes), 1981, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - FBI Files #100-100351 (volume 10) and #100-37819 (volume 1) requested by Sylvia Thompson, 1953-1958 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - FBI File #100-7320 (volume 1) requested by Sylvia Thompson, 1946-1954 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - FBI File #100-100351 (volumes 11,20) requested by Sylvia Thompson, 1958-1960 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - FBI File #100-100351 (volumes 4,24) requested by Sylvia Thompson, 1952-1965 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - FBI Files #100-100351 (volume 29) and #100-4495 requested by Sylvia Thompson, 1951-1971 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Kreisberg correspondence with #100-100351 excerpt, explanation of FBI exemptions and FOIA Files Kit, 1980-1988 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Cassette tape "Nuchow interview" and encased coin commemorating 50th anniversary of Antifascist Spanish War, 1985-1986; cuid198 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - William Nuchow Interview, 1985-08-06; cuid199 (Box 2, Cassette 1, Box Shared Access TAM Box 1, Cd 1)
- Series III: Thompson v. McNamara Trial Materials
  Series III "Thompson v. McNamara" contains materials related to Sylvia Thompson's efforts to have her late husband interred in Arlington National Cemetery. It includes court documents exhibits and briefs, press clippings, photographs and correspondence. Also included is "The Arlington Case: Robert Thompson-story of an unburied soldier," which is a pamphlet published by Sylvia Thompson in 1967 in an effort to publicize her attempts at interring her husband in Arlington National Cemetery.
  - Thompson v. McNamara correspondence, 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Thompson v. McNamara correspondence, 1965-1968 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Thompson v. McNamara Exhibits, 1941-1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Thompson v. McNamara-Legal 1 USCA Arlington, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Thompson v. McNamara-Legal 2 Briefs and Pleadings USDC, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
  - Arlington: Legal (Briefs) 3, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Arlington: Legal 4, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Arlington: Legal 4, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Arlington: Legal 4, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Final judgment and original petition of Sylvia Thompson, 1966-1969 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Clippings-Denial of Arlington burial, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Article published in "Tresa" Lithuania U.S.S.R., Jan 28, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Congressional Record Clippings, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Clippings-granting Arlington burial, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - The Arlington Case: Robert Thompson-story of an unburied soldier, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - New York Post clipping on Thompson disability benefits, Jun 29, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Thompson v. McNamara (press releases), 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - [Correspondence and clippings regarding Arlington burial], 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - [Correspondence and clippings regarding Arlington burial], 1966 (Box 3, Folder 20)